<SECTION>
    <NAME>History of Egyptian Fractions</NAME>
    <LABEL NAME="sec:history-ef"/>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>

    <TEXT>
        [<EM>
This section talks about the history of Egyptian Fractions that started from
        Ancient Egypt.
    </EM>]
    </TEXT>


    <TEXT>
        Egyptians used hieroglyphs to represent their numbers (Knott 2020).
        When they use fractions, an eye above the number to represent the unit
        fractions. There are also special fractions which are commonly used by
        the Egyptians. These are seen in the pictures below.
    </TEXT>

    <FIGURE>
        <FIGURE src="img_egypt/notation.png"></FIGURE>
        <LABEL NAME="fig:notation"/>
        <CAPTION>Fractions in Egyptian Hieroglyphs. (Humenberger,
            <EM>figure 1</EM>)
        </CAPTION>
    </FIGURE>

    <FIGURE>
        <FIGURE src="img_egypt/specialfractions.png"></FIGURE>
        <LABEL NAME="fig:special-fractions"/>
        <CAPTION>Special Fractions Without 1 as Numerator (Bruaw,
            <EM>Common Fractions</EM>)
        </CAPTION>
    </FIGURE>

    <TEXT>
        As mentioned previously, Egyptians are limited in their representations of
        fractions but still needed a method of dividing wages among the workers.
        For example, when there are 5 sacks of rice as wages, the Egyptians used
        these fractions to split them among their 6 workers. In these cases, they
        built a table of fractions to keep track of how to divide the wages.
        This is evidenced by the Rhind Papyrus which came from about 1850BC
        <INDEX>Brown, Kevin</INDEX> (Brown n.d.)
        which is a table of Egyptian Fraction representations for fractions
        of the form <LATEXINLINE>$\frac{2}{n}$</LATEXINLINE> as listed in
        Richard Gilling's book in 1976 <INDEX>Gilling, Richard</INDEX>
        <INDEX>Gong, Kevin</INDEX> (Gong 1992).
    </TEXT>

    <FIGURE src="img_egypt/SurreyAhmesPapyrus.png">
        <LABEL NAME="fig:rhind"/>
        <CAPTION>Rhind Papyrus Table of Egyptian Fractions (Knott,
             <EM>Ahmes Papyrus</EM>)
        </CAPTION>
    </FIGURE>

    <TEXT>
        With such tables, the Egyptians can use the unit fractions to decide how to
        split the wages. For example,
    </TEXT>

    <LATEX>
        \[\frac{5}{6} = \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{3}\]
    </LATEX>

    <FIGURE src="img_egypt/sack.jpg">
        <LABEL NAME="fig:example-wages-1"/>
        <CAPTION>5 Bags of Rice for 6 Workers
        </CAPTION>
    </FIGURE>

    <TEXT>
        This means that they can split the 5 bags into 2 groups. 3 of the bags can
        be split into halves while the other 2 can be split into thirds. From these,
        the taskmaster can give each worker a half and a third. This makes it
        easier for Egyptian taskmasters to give out wages for their workers. This is
        different from our modern methods of simply dividing each bag into 6 parts
        and giving each worker 5 of these parts. Here is an illustration.
    </TEXT>

    <FIGURE src="img_egypt/sack2.jpg">
        <LABEL NAME="fig:example-wages-2"/>
        <CAPTION>5 Bags of Rice for 6 Workers Split Equally
        </CAPTION>
    </FIGURE>

    <TEXT>
        This example shows how Egyptian Fraction representations are different from
        our usage of ordinary fractions with a numerator greater than 1. Though it
        is not obvious how the Egyptians derive these representations, they seem to
        indicate the Egyptians used advanced mathematical concepts like the Sieve
        of Eratosthenes and practical numbers. This allows room for mathematical
        research in this area, which has been growing over the years.
    </TEXT>



</SECTION>
