<SECTION>
    <NAME>Application of Egyptian Fractions</NAME>
    <LABEL NAME="sec:application"/>

    <TEXT>
        [<EM>
This section gives some examples of application of Egyptian Fractions in other
        subjects.
    </EM>]
    </TEXT>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>

    <TEXT>
        <INDEX>Kosheleva, Olga</INDEX>
        Egyptian Fractions may not seem useful at first glance. However, there
        are a few areas of application. For example, Olga Kosheleva, Vladik
        Kreinovich and Francisco Zapata (2009) have explored using unit
        fractions in modern computers for division. This is because some
        computers do not do division directly but uses multiplication with
        the reciprocal instead. In these cases, Egyptian Fractions may be
        applied such that reciprocals or unit fractions can be useful for
        division computations.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        <INDEX>Schwartz, Jeffery</INDEX> <INDEX>Brown, Kevin</INDEX>
        Another application found by Professor Jeffrey Schwartz (2018) is
        looking at resistors placed in parallel in a circuit. When resistors
        are placed in parallel, their total resistance is the inverse of the
        sum of the reciprocals of the individual resistances, ie.
    </TEXT>

    <LATEX>
        \[\frac{1}{R_{tot}} = \frac{1}{R_1} + \frac{1}{R_2} + ... \]
    </LATEX>

    <TEXT>
        The right hand side has a similar representation as Egyptian Fractions.
        One possible way to make use of this is to come up with resistance
        values to get nicer round numbers for students that are learning about
        parallel resistors. Another possibility is to use the standard values
        of resistors and get the total resistance more easily instead of the
        usual tedious method of cross-multiplying and flipping the fractions.
        There is another similar problem called the 2 Ohm problem by Kevin
        Brown (n.d.).
    </TEXT>


    <TEXT>
        <INDEX>Torfs, Wim</INDEX>
        Another area of application is in wireless sensor networks. Wim Torfs
        and Chris Blondia (2010) found that Egyptian Fractions can be used for
        representing fractions with binary trees in a Time Division Multiple
        Access scheduling algorithm to create a flexible and stable
        wireless sensor network. Egyptian Fractions allows the scheduling to be
        periodic and also works as an approximation as only fractions have
        denominators that are powers of 2 are used.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        These are just a few areas of application of Egyptian Fractions and
        there could be more that have not yet been explored.
    </TEXT>

</SECTION>
