<CHAPTER>
    <NAME>
        Egyptian Fractions
    </NAME>

    <HISTORY>
        % fall '97 Add tex '\label's for manual to reference.
        % 8/26/97  FIX TYPOS FOR THIRD PRINTING -- p.45, p.70
        %
        % 4/15/96 FIX TYPO FOUND BY COMPARING TO BEFORE-INDEXING -- MUST REPRINT P.60
        % 4/13-4/15 Indexing [after final printout of chapters]
        % 4/11 Corrections and adjustments based on <QUOTE>final</QUOTE> check and
        % spell-checking
        % 4/9  trivial fixes based on comparison to before-indexing
        % 4/6-... Julie index fixes (and 4/8 change 'ns')
        % 4/5/96 Hal indexing
        % 3/29/96, 4/3/96 Julie: indexing fixes
        % 3/18/96 rest of pagination, minor other indexing changes
        % 3/14 &amp; 3/16/96 Paginated up to p.64 (look for \pagekludge)
        % 3/10-3/14/96 minor changes/fixes; indexing; Moved exercise
        % 3/9/96  fix spacing in some exercise parts
        % 3/6/96  fix typos
        % 3/5/96  minor typesetting fixes
        % 3/4/96  edit first-class-proc footnote for PSZ; fix minor error
        % 2/26-3/1/96 fix some bad line breaks
        % 2/24/96 flush \noindent after {lisp} by closing up space with %
        % 2/24/96 fix format of GCD-reduction equation
        % 2/23/96 fix typesetting with new smallequation macro
        % 2/22/96 new spec for epigraph
        % 2/21/96 fixed format of absolute-value def
        % 2/20/96 fix how arrows are done
        % 2/19/96 changed exp-iter -> expt-iter, fast-exp -> fast-expt
        % 2/19/96 fixed () in a reference
        % 2/19/96 fixed et al.
    </HISTORY>

    <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

    <TEXT>
        Egyptian fractions are a unique way of representing and using fractions.
        This is because the Ancient Egyptians only used unit fractions which are
        fractions that have a numerator of 1. In other words, they only used
        reciprocals as fractions. For example,
        <LATEX>
            $\frac{1}{3}, \frac{1}{14}, 2^{-1}$
        </LATEX>
        are used by the Egyptians but
        <LATEX>
            $\frac{5}{6}, \frac{2}{14}$
        </LATEX>
        are not because their numerators are not 1. Hence, a different method is
        required to represent these fractions that have a numerator greater than 1.
        The Egyptians represented their fractions with positive, distinct unit
        fractions. Looking at the first example fraction,
        <LATEX>
            \[\frac{5}{6} = \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{3}\]
        </LATEX>
        <LATEX>
            \[\frac{5}{6} = \frac{1}{2} + \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{12}\]
        </LATEX>
        These representations are correct because they represent the fraction with
        distinct unit fractions. However, these examples would be wrong:
        <LATEX>
            \[\frac{5}{6} = \frac{1}{3} + \frac{1}{4} + \frac{1}{4}\]
        </LATEX>
        This is wrong because the denominators in the second and third unit
        fractions are the same. Since the unit fractions are not distinct, this is
        an invalid representation.
        <LATEX>
            \[\frac{5}{6} = \frac{1}{1} - \frac{1}{6}\]
        </LATEX>
        This would also be wrong because the second unit fraction used is negative.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        Though Egyptian Fractions may seem vastly different from programming, it
        can help to explain the rationale of various essential concepts in
        programming to beginner students. Fractions are something basic that
        students have learnt at a young age and this could be useful in helping
        them to understand computing concepts which may be too abstract to grasp
        initially. This makes programming easier to grasp for new students. At the
        same time, the mathematical complexity behind Egyptian Fractions can
        engage students that can grasp the programming concepts easily. Egyptian
        Fractions can also provide context for the programs implemented.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        This is adapted from Martin Henz's book called ``Structure and
        Interpretation of Computer Programs - JavaScript Adaptation" which can be
        found online at (https://source-academy.github.io/sicp/). This will cover
        the same concepts and will also be teaching JavaScript with the online
        environment developed by Henz (https://sourceacademy.nus.edu.sg/playground).
        This provides a platform for students to learn programming with
        JavaScript in a more accessible manner.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        (Just to test whether I can type in something here and be able to
        display on the internet)
        <SNIPPET>
            <JAVASCRIPT>
                const egyptians = 4;
                egyptians;
            </JAVASCRIPT>
        </SNIPPET>
        by clicking it, it will respond by creating a separate
        browser tab where the statement is shown, with the option
        to evaluate the statement by pressing a <QUOTE>Run</QUOTE> button.
        Click on the primitive expression statement, and see what happens!
    </TEXT>

    <CHAPTERCONTENT/>

    <!-- Section 1 : History of Egyptian Fractions -->
    &section0.1;

    <!-- Section 2 : Work Done on Egyptian Fractions -->
    &section0.2;

    <!-- Section 3 : Application of Egyptian Fractions -->
    &section0.3;

    <!-- Section 4 : Using Natural Numbers Only -->
    &section0.4;

</CHAPTER>
