<SECTION>
    <NAME>Work Done on Egyptian Fractions</NAME>
    <LABEL NAME="sec:work-done"/>

    <SECTIONCONTENT/>
    <TEXT>
        [<EM>
This section discusses the work on Egyptian Fraction algorithms and introduces
        the Egyptian Fraction algorithms in a more detailed manner in the
        next subesction.
    </EM>]
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        While the ancient Egyptians had a large table, it does not contain all the
        fractions. Researchers have explored whether these types of fractions can be
        expanded to all possible fractions. Over the years, many have researched
        regarding whether all fractions have an Egyptian Fraction representation.
        Not only that, there has also been research done on various mathematical
        methods to find Egyptian Fractions in a more efficient manner or for a
        better output. This is a brief overview of what work has been done on
        Egyptian Fractions.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        The very first algorithm was found by Fibonacci in 1202
        <INDEX>Sigler, Laurence</INDEX> (Sigler 2002) which was rediscovered by
        <INDEX>Sylvester, James</INDEX> Sylvester (1880). This was known as the
        <INDEX>Egyptian Fraction Algorithms<SUBINDEX>Greedy</SUBINDEX></INDEX>
        Greedy Algorithm. Following their work, other mathematicians, like Paul
        Erd<LATEXINLINE>\"{o}</LATEXINLINE>s have come up with algorithms such
        as the <INDEX>Egyptian Fraction Algorithms<SUBINDEX>Splitting</SUBINDEX>
        </INDEX> Splitting Algorithm and the <INDEX>Egyptian Fraction Algorithms
        <SUBINDEX>Continued Fractions</SUBINDEX></INDEX> Continued Fractions
        algorithm. While these algorithms have been found, not all have
        been proven to be mathematically valid.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        Over the many years, other mathematicians and computer scientists
        build on their work by proving conjectures in the algorithms and
        proving the correctness and termination of these algorithms. For
        example, <INDEX>Erd<LATEXINLINE>\"{o}</LATEXINLINE>s, Paul</INDEX>
        Erd<LATEXINLINE>\"{o}</LATEXINLINE>s and <INDEX>Bleicher, M.N.</INDEX>
        Bleicher (1976) ends off with some conjectures in his paper. In the
        following years, people have worked on proving conjectures
        based on Egyptian Fraction algorithms, for example,
         <INDEX>Yokota, Hisashi</INDEX> <INDEX>Beeckmans, Laurel</INDEX>
        Hisashi Yokota (1986) built on one of the conjectures made by
        Erd<LATEXINLINE>\"{o}</LATEXINLINE>s<APOS/> and Bleicher. Another
        example is Laurel Beeckmans (1993) who worked on conjectures for the
        Splitting algorithm.
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <INDEX>Martin, Greg</INDEX>
        Mathematical properties of the algorithms are also being explored, such
        as bounds of the largest denominators and the number of unit fractions
        in the expansion (Martin 1999). Others have also worked on improving
        and optimising current algorithms (Yokota 1987) (Martin 1998).
        <INDEX>Gong, Kevin</INDEX> <INDEX>Zanardo, Alberto</INDEX>
        Not just that, others have compiled the algorithms and have done some
        comparisons based on these mathematical properties (Gong 1992)
        (Zanardo 2018).
    </TEXT>
    <TEXT>
        <INDEX>Bello-Herandez</INDEX> <INDEX>Hagedorn, Thomas</INDEX>
        <INDEX>Croot</INDEX> <INDEX>Huang, Jingjing</INDEX>
        <INDEX>Negash, Dagnachew J.</INDEX>
        Egyptian Fractions are closely linked to number theory problems such as
        the Diophantine equation and semiperfect numbers.
        Diophantine equation refers to equations that only have integer
        solutions and the Erd<LATEXINLINE>\"{o}</LATEXINLINE>s-Straus Conjecture
        is a well-known one (Manuel Bello-Harnández, Benito, and Fernández,
        2012). This conjecture resulted in many researchers taking up the
        challenge in solving it (Croot 1999) (Thomas Hagedorn 2000) (Croot et
        al. 2000) (Negash 2001). Other than the conjecture, there are also
        other Diophantine equations that are explored (Huang and Vaughan 2011).
        <INDEX>Friedman, Charles</INDEX>
        Semiperfect numbers are natural numbers that are equal to the sum of
        certain of its distinct positive proper divisors that is not itself
        (Friedman 1991). The nature of the semiperfect numbers fit in with
        Egyptian Fractions that also only use natural numbers, making Egyptian
        Fractions applicable to semiperfect numbers.
    </TEXT>

    <TEXT>
        <INDEX>Eppstein, David</INDEX>
        Others have also worked on implementing Egyptian Fractions in other
        computing languages like Mathematica (Eppstein 2009) and ANSI C
        (Gong 1992), which have been used as reference for the algorithms
        implemented in this book for Egyptian Fractions. The algorithms have
        been adapted to go through the essential concepts in programming with
        the JavaScript language.
    </TEXT>

    <!-- Subsection 1 : Algorithms-->
    &subsection0.2.1;

</SECTION>
