<SUBSECTION>
  <NAME>Work Done on Egyptian Fractions</NAME>
  <LABEL NAME="sec:work-done"></LABEL>

  <TEXT>
    While the ancient Egyptians had a large table, it does not contain all the
    fractions. Researchers have explored whether these types of fractions can be
    expanded to all possible fractions. Over the years, many have researched
    regarding whether all fractions have an Egyptian Fraction representation.
    Not only that, there has also been research done on various mathematical
    methods to find Egyptian Fractions in a more efficient manner or for a
    better output. This is a brief overview of what work has been done on
    Egyptian Fractions.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    Work has been done since 1880, when the first known algorithm was discovered
    by Fibonacci and Sylvester called the Fibonacci-Sylveter Algorithm. This is
    more commonly known as the Greedy method. With this method, it can be proven
     that all fractions can have an Egyptian Fraction representation, which will
    be explored more later on. In more recent years, famous mathematican Paul
    Erdos has also done research on this topic and have published works on it,
    regarding optimising algorithms as well as proposing conjectures regarding
    Egyptian Fractions.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    As centuries passed, different algorithms and conjectures were formed by
    mathematicians anc computer scientists. Some formed newer algorithms like
    the Continued Fraction method while others have taken to proving validity
    and/or termination of algorithms and the conjectures. Mathematical
    properties of the algorithms were also explored, such as bounds of the
    largest denominators and the number of terms found. Others have also worked
    on improving and optimising current algorithms. Expanding beyond Egyptian
    Fractions, researchers have also linked this topic to number theory, like
    the Diophantine equation and Znam's Problem.
  </TEXT>

  <TEXT>
    Others have also worked on implementing Egyptian Fractions in other
    computing languages like Mathematica, which has also been used as reference
    for the algorithms implemented in this book for Egyptian Fractions. The
    algorithms have been adapted to go through the essential concepts in
    programming with the JavaScript language.
  </TEXT>

</SUBSECTION>


